Finding Aid for United Church of Christ Women of Michigan Records 1915-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United Church of Christ Women of Michigan Records 1915-2013 1945-2013
United Church of Christ Women of Michigan
2.5 linear feet.
Record books and other records, including minutes, correspondence, annual reports, directories, newsletters and other materials relating to their activities, as well as historical essays.
03166 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records (donor no. 9368 ) were received August 19, 2003 from the United Church of Christ Women of Michigan. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open for research.
The United Church of Christ Women (UCC Women) can trace its beginnings to the first meeting of the Michigan Branch of the Women's Board of Missions of the Interior in 1874. It was the first state-wide organization for women active in the Congregational Church. By 1915, there were two active groups: the Michigan Branch of the Women's Board of Missions of the Interior and the Woman's Home Missionary Union. In 1926, the two groups merged and became The Women's Missionary Society of the Michigan Congregational Conference. In 1936, the group adopted a new constitution and became the Women's Department of Michigan Congregational Christian Conference. The name was changed to the Women's Fellowship in 1943. In 1964, the group merged with the Evangelical and Reformed Women's Guild (formed in 1940 with members from Michigan and Indiana). Finally, in 1980, the group adopted the name UCC Women of Michigan.
The UCC Women of Michigan coordinate the activities of the regional UCC Women groups and sets annual goals. Within the group, they have the divisions of Social Concerns, Christian Education, Spiritual Life and Evangelism, and Material Aids and Missionary Education. They also promote cooperation with other Christian groups. In 1987, the UCC Women began a relationship with the Michigan Region of the Christian Church Disciples of Christ women. The two groups attend each other's meetings and retreats, hold joint meetings, and have established "clusters" of regional groups for interaction and Bible study.
The UCC Women have a dual purpose, to maintain a bond between the women in the group and help their individual spiritual development, and to reach out to the community and the world to promote Christianity and relieve suffering. For individual development, they study together and hold an annual, week-long retreat every summer for members. Their outreach program consists of monetary donations and collecting items to send as relief within the United States and throughout the world. They also provide scholarships to women, both clergy and lay, for education. One of their projects has been to provide substantial support to the Madras Women's Christian College in India.
Current information is available at http://www.ucc.org/women/index.html The site is part of the education page of the national United Church of Christ, and includes a digital archive of the quarterly newsletter "Common Lot," which the UCC Women help support.
The UCC Women records are mainly composed of records from the organization's meetings and information for the annual retreats. Records are from as early as 1915, and are available for most years from 1945-1962 and all years from 1962-2008. The records are divided into three series. Record books, Annual Records, and Other Records.
Subjects:
Congregational churches--Michigan.; Evangelical and Reformed Church--Michigan.; United Church of Christ--Michigan.; United Church of Christ Women of Michigan.; Woman's Home Missionary Union of Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan.
- Record Books
  The Record Books series consists of six volumes of records. Book I contains salvaged records of the earlier women's groups, mostly meeting minutes, ranging from 1915-1944. Books II-V contain the reports of the annual meetings of the Women's Fellowship Michigan Congregational Christian Conference, as well as retreat information and correspondence pertaining to the group activities. They cover most years from 1945-1974. Book VI contains the records of the UCC Women of Michigan from 1974-1979.
  - 1915-1945 (Book I; scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - 1945-1955 (Book II) (Box 1)
  - 1956-1960 (Book III) (Box 1)
  - 1961-1964 (Book IV) (Box 1)
  - 1964-1974 (Book V) (Box 1)
  - 1974-1979 (Book VI) (Box 1)
- Annual Records
  The second series, Annual Records, covers every year from 1962 to 2007 and contains the minutes and reports from the annual meetings, as well as minutes from board meetings throughout the year.
  - 1962-1969, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - 1970-2012/13, 43 folders (Box 2)
- Other Records
  The Other Records series consists of newsletters, bylaws and organizational manuals, and membership directories, records of the UCC Women of Michigan Investment Committee; also included essays on the history of UCCW and UCC Women of Michigan.
  - Newsletter: The Communicator, 2001-2008 (Box 3)
  - Bylaws and manual, 1975, 1983, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Directories, 1963/64-2006/07, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - History of UCCW (Box 3)
  - UCC Women of Michigan Investment Committee File, 1975-1987 (scattered years) (Box 3)